A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, 1957-2005 (bulk 1985-1991)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, 1957-2005 (bulk 1985-1991)
The Library of Virginia
51069, 53118, 53131
12.35 cu. ft. (13 boxes)
Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years (Code of Virginia 42.1-78). Types of information records restricted may include but are not limited to: personal information (2.2-3801). It is necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain privacy protected or confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies can be made. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
Acquisition Information
Gifted on 17 July 2013 by A.E. Dick Howard, Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 [Acc. 51069].
Gifted on 28 August 2020 by A.E. Dick Howard, Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 [Acc. 53118].
Gifted on 9 September 2020 by Timothy G. O'Rourke, Virginia Beach, Virginia 23456 [Acc. 53131].
Biographical Information
The Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution was created in 1985 by an Act of the General Assembly. Its charge was to "plan and develop activities appropriate to commemorate the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, including events leading to the Constitution's drafting, its ratification, and the adoption of the Bill of Rights." Timothy G. O'Rourke served as the Executive Director, A.E. Dick Howard served as the Commission Chair, and Billie Easton served as Special Events Director.
Scope and Content
Records, 1957-2005 (bulk 1985-1991), of the Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution. There are correspondence, subject files, reports, and other material relating to the planning of events to commemorate the Bicentennial that were collected by Commission chairman A. E. Dick Howard. These include invitations to groups, public relations material, and fundraising material, among many others. There are also newspaper clippings of articles that relate to the Bicentennial.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Records, 1984-1992 [Acc. 51069]
Series II: Records, 1980-1992 [Acc. 53118]
Series I: Records, 1957-2005 [Acc. 53131]
Contents List
- Series I: Records, 1984-1992 [Acc. 51069], Extent: 4 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 1-4)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-13)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4-11)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annual reports, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 9-16)
- Series I: Records, 1980-1992 [Acc. 53118], Extent: 5 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and publications, 1982-1989 (Box 1)
  - National Bicentennial Competition on the Constitution and Bill of Rights, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Conference of States on Bicentennial Planning, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AALS - Bicentennial, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ABA - Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Colonial Williamsburg, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Competitions, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Conference of Chief Justices, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Congress, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Court Days (U. Va. Institute of Government), 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Debates (Burger), 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Constitutional Decade, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Defense, Department of, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Delaware, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Federal Judicial Center, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Federal Commission: International Advisory Group, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - First Amendment Congress, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - George Mason University - Project for the Study of Human Rights, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Governance in Future Space Communities, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jefferson Meeting on the Constitution, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - KQED, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Maryland, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 'The Media and the Constitution' - Williamsburg, VA, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mentor Group, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Conference, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Constitution: A Work in Progress, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kaminski - Vol III, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hamilton/Distribution of WFF, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Forum (Bicentennial Symposium issue), 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Park Service, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Portrait Gallery, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Radio Theatre, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New Hampshire, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Project '87, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Project '87: Exhibits, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Project '87, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Commission on the Bicentennial, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Jefferson Foundation, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Project '87 Media Task Force, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Virginia Jefferson Association, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - WETA - Telecourse on 'The Courts', 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - WETA - Supreme Court series, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - We the People 200, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - WGBH, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - William & Mary, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - WNET, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - WNET / Thirteen, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Channel 13, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - WVIA-TV - 'Understanding Government', 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Understanding Government - Supreme Court Project, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Universities/Colleges, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bill of Rights, 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - State Commissions, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - USIA, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspapers, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Cons. Comm., 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Publications, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bicentennial Publications, 1981-1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Publications, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and Publications, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Publications, 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Publications, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Publications, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Jefferson Meeting on Constitution, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Space Governance, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - WETA, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - KQED, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Selected Bicentennial Celebrations, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Constitution Project, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Magna Carta, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - State Committee On Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Constitution Council, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bicentennial Commission, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - ABA-Bicentennial Cons., 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series I: Records, 1957-2005 [Acc. 53131], Extent: 3.35 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 1-4)
  - Commemorative Items, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pocket Constitutions, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Banners, nd (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bicentennial of the Constitution, 1984-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Checklist for Planning Special Events, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Workshop notes, 1992 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Workshop on Special Events Planning, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corrected Table of Contents for Special Events Checklist, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Certificate of Appreciation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Government in Brief & Virginia's Capitol Square, 1957-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Center for Public Service, University of Virginia, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Constitution folders, nd (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - VBC Annual Reports, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - VBC stationary, nd (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Shark Poster Explanation, nd (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - VBC - Staff Addresses Inventory/Remaining Materials, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Historic Homes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Congressional Delegation/Virginia, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Commissioners' Checklist, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Speech to Va. PRSA, 1987 May (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Commendations/VA Institute of Govt, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - June 11 & June 25 - Commendations, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Montpelier - Commendations, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Virginia Day - Commendations, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Symposium: Central and Eastern Europe, 1991 June 10-11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Conseil d'Etat Visit, 1989 September 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Goncz Visit, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibit Opening: Montpelier, 1989 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Reapportionment Conference, 1989 December 11-12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - State Fair Booth, 1990 September (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Shark Poster Explanation/Bill of Rights Film Study Guide, nd (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Documentary Film, nd (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ideas Packets, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Les Droits Program - Power Line (Monpelier Event) - Montpelier Memento, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Virginia Association of Realtors, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Protocol Guide, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Center for Civic Education, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Checklist for Planning Special Events, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Events, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - The Global Legacy of the Bill of Rights, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Photographs, Mr. and Mrs. Robert Greenhow of Williamsburg, nd (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bill of Rights Bicentennial Programs and Resources Conference, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - The Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Press clippings, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - The Global Legacy of the Bill of Rights - Goncz Visit, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Goncz Visit, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Checklist for Planning Special Events, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Grave site Ceremony Honoring Thomas Mathews, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - "Les Droits de l'Homme and Scientific Progress" - Smithsonian/UVA Conference, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Virginia State Fair, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - A Dominion Divided: Madison-Henry Debates, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Montpelier Opening, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Day in Philadelphia, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - The Virginia Assembly, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Special Events Checklist, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Well Begun and Life Magazine, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Life Magazine, 1987-1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - VBC Brochures and Programs, 1987-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Map of Virginia, Commonwealth Studies Program, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Federal Commission Calendars, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Banner (oversize)